Finding Aid for the William J. Donovan Papers, 1913-1920
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
William J. Donovan Papers
1913 - 1920
Mss. B86-6
Donovan, William J. (William Joseph), 1883-1959
3 boxes (1.5 linear feet)
The correspondence and printed material relating to Captain (later Colonel) William J. Donovan's military service, his legal career in Buffalo with O' Brian, Hamlin, Donovan & Goodyear, and his involvement with the American Legion and Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Association.
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The William J. Donovan Papers, 1913-1920, are open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Smyton, James W.; gift; 1984/12/05; unknown
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
William J. Donovan was raised in Buffalo, educated at Miss Nardin's Private School and St. Joseph's Collegiate Institute; he attended Niagara University for two years before transferring to Columbia, where he earned his A.B. in 1905 and LL.B. in 1907.
Donovan began his legal career in Buffalo with Love & Keating. In 1912, he formed a partnership that was to become the firm of O'Brian, Hamlin, Donovan & Goodyear (dissolved 1920).
Concurrently he actively pursued a military career, becoming one of the founders of Troop I, 1st Cavalry of the New York National Guard, elected as captain in 1912. In 1915, he visited Europe for the War Relief Commission; he returned to serve on the Mexican border with Troop I, then underwent training in a number of military camps, convinced that the United States' entry into World War I was inevitable. He sailed for Europe with the Rainbow Division, one of the first to mobilize, and soon became a battalion major in the "Fighting 69th" New York Infantry (known in France as 165th). Donovan was rapidly promoted to lt. colonel, then colonel.
During World War I, he was highly decorated for his leadership and heroism, receiving the Croix de Guerre, Distinguished Service Cross, the Legion of Honor medal and the Italian War Cross. After being discharged in May 1919, he sailed for Asia to investigate the White Russian government of Aleksandr Kolchak in Siberia, who was then struggling against the Bolsheviks.
In 1922, Donovan ran unsuccessfully for lt. governor of New York; in 1932 he was defeated in his bid for New York's governorship. President Harding appointed him U.S. attorney for the western district of New York in 1922; he met with considerable success prosecuting major crime rings until 1924.
Donovan resumed his law practice in Buffalo until special duties during World War II forced him to abandon it. Franklin Roosevelt assigned him to coordinate information for the Joint Chiefs, and promoted him to brigadier general and later to major general.
Donovan was also instrumental in helping to establish the Office of Strategic Services, later the Central Intelligence Agency.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence and printed material relating to Captain (later Colonel) Donovan's military service with the 1st Cavalry, New York National Guard, and then with the "Fighting 69th" New York Infantry in World War I; his legal career in Buffalo with O'Brian, Hamlin, Donovan & Goodyear; and his involvement with the American Legion, Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Association, and Columbia University, circa 1915-1920. Correspondents include Douglas MacArthur.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in ten series:
I. Correspondence
II. Siberia Trip
III. Post World War I: Europe and Asia
IV. Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Association
V. Columbia University Alumni Activities
VI. Purchases
VII. Cards and Announcements
VIII. American Legion
IX. Printed Material
X. Miscellaneous Manuscripts.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1914-1920, I.
  - Legal, 1914-1915, I.A.
    - 1914 (Box-folder 1.1)
    - 1915 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Personal, 1913-1920, I.B.
    - 1913-1914 (Box-folder 1.3)
    - January-August 1915 (Box-folder 1.4)
    - September-December 1915 (Box-folder 1.5)
    - January-February 1916 (Box-folder 1.6)
    - March-December 1916 (Box-folder 1.7)
    - January-December 1917 (Box-folder 1.8)
    - 1918 (Box-folder 1.9)
    - February-May 1919 (Box-folder 1.10)
    - June-September 1919 (Box-folder 1.11)
    - October 1919 (Box-folder 2.1-2.2)
    - November 1919 (Box-folder 2.3)
    - January-May 1920 (Box-folder 2.4)
    - June 1920 (Box-folder 2.5)
    - July-October 1920 (Box-folder 2.6)
  - Military, 1917-1920; I.C.
    - 1917 (Box-folder 2.7)
    - 1919 (Box-folder 2.8)
    - 1920 (Box-folder 2.9)
  - Telegrams, 1915-1920, I.D.
    - 1915-1916, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3.1)
- Siberia trip, 1919, II.
  - Siberia Trip, 1919 (Box-folder 3.2)
- Post World War I: Europe and Asia, 1919, III.
  - Post World War I: Europe and Asia, 1919 (Box-folder 3.3)
- Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1919-1920, IV.
  - Theodore Roosevelt Memorial Association, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3.4)
- Columbia University Alumni Activities, undated, V.
  - Columbia University Alumni Activities, undated (Box-folder 3.5)
- Purchases, 1915-1920, VI.
  - General, 1915-1919 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Books, 1915, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 3.7)
- Cards and Announcements, undated, VII.
  - Cards and Announcements, undated (Box-folder 3.8)
- American Legion, 1919-1920, VIII.
  - American Legion, 1919-1920, undated (Box-folder 3.9)
- Printed Material, undated, IX.
  - Printed Material, undated (Box-folder 3.10-3.11)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts, undated, X.
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts, undated (Box-folder 3.12)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964; O'Brian, Hamlin, Donovan & Goodyear (Buffalo, N.Y.); Roosevelt Memorial Association; Buffalo History Museum
Subject Terms
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Columbia University--Alumni and alumnae; World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 69th (1861-1865); Law offices--New York (State)--Buffalo; Siberia--History--Revolution, 1917-1921
Genre Terms
Correspondence